Hello everyone, welcome to this video.
In this video, we'll be discussing about
quite a few topics that includes the
workflow events and how do we keep the
human in the workflow for reviewer and
approval purposes and we will also be
discussing about checkpoints. So first
we will begin with the workflow events.
Microsoft agent framework uses the event
based system within its workflow
feature. These events are published
throughout the workflow execution that
allow the developers to monitor and
debug and control the workflow
execution.
So again these uh events will help us
with the observability. You can you know
use these events to debug on auditing
purposes that will let you decouple your
workflow logic with you know your logic
that will also keep the context in sync
as well as you can you know dynamically
control the overall workflow execution.
So when I see the events what does it
mean? So if I just come over here if you
see here like let's assume that I have a
workflow with three different nodes.
It's a sequential workflow with the
three different nodes here. So first we
will begin with the parse text, convert
text and explain text right. So if you
see the events when you start the
workflow this particular event will
trigger. So this will say hey like
workflow it's started and then like
workflow status will change from starter
to in progress and like the executor
will get invoked and that event will get
triggered. So basically like this
particular executor will get invoked.
Then you will see the uh executor
result. The executor will say like I'm
done. Then the next executor will get
called. Then it is you know results.
Then it will get completed. Then finally
like the this particular executor will
get called its results and it will get
completed. Finally the workflow itself
will get completed. So as you see here
like from one fees to another fees as
the workflow moves you these events will
get triggered that provides lot of
information to us. So for instance if
you see here so here like we can start a
timer saying that hey like the workflow
started you know at this particular time
and finally we can say like this
workflow took this many seconds or
minutes to complete the execution as
well as if at all you wanted to control
something then you can very well do it
within these events. So if you see here
we can you know break down these events
into four different categories. So first
we will have a workflow life cycle
events. So again um it will say like
workflow started, workflow completed,
workflow output, error, warning or
whatever is that all of these events are
directly associated with the workflow
itself. Then you will have something
called superep. So basically like you
can split the workflow into any number
of logical pieces. Right? So if you
think of this way so this this entire
thing it's a workflow but let's assume
that the force text and convert text
it's one logical group and like this
explain text it's another logical group.
So in this particular workflow in this
particular case you will have two
different superstep. So again superep
it's nothing but the logical group right
of a workflow. So you you can also have
events for that. then the executor
events. So again like if I just come
over here here we have three different
executors. So for each executor you will
have the executor related events. So you
can also have that you know invoked,
completed, failed, run event, response
event and all of these events. Then
finally you will also have the request
info event. So basically like when you
want to uh get some information
externally then you can use this request
info event. If you want to learn more
about these events then you can use this
reference article that clearly explains
all these events and how do we use this.
Right now we know that what are all
these events we will go back to the
visual studio and see like how do we use
these uh events.
So what we want to do is that we want to
build a simple workflow. So basically
like this is the workflow that I want to
build right. So you will be having a
simple sequential workflow exactly the
same workflow we are going to build. So
first you need to import all the events.
These events are part of this agent
framework. So you need to import
whatever the events that you are
interested in. You can import all of
these events. So as you see here like I
have three different uh class uh you
know executors. I will be building a
simple sequential workflow from parser
to converter convert to the explainer.
Then when you say like workflow
runstream it will emit a lot of events.
You can check the type of that
particular event. So here I'm saying
like if the event is a type of workflow
started then you say workflow started
and like print the workflow ID. If it is
you know status event you will print the
status like whatever the status you know
right now it has. So we will print that.
In this particular case like all of
these events are more of a observability
uh events. You can only you know print
some of these information extract some
of these information from the workflow
execution. But there are quite a few uh
you know events that let you dynamically
control the workflow. So now if you just
come down here like likewise like I
captured all the events that I'm
interested in executor invoked executor
convoked uh completed and the like
workflow output workflow failed workflow
failed executor failed event or whatever
is that so like whatever I am interested
in I am going to just you know log all
this information in the console that
like let me go and run this. So this so
if I run it here you see here like it
says that workflow started and this is
the workflow ID. Each workflow will have
its you know ID and like the workflow
status event occurred in progress and we
extracted some of these events. If you
see here like extraction should happen
in the parser executor right. So if you
see here like executor invoked ideally
like it has to come between uh invoked
and completed. But because like as we
are using the async if I just come over
here this is the async operation right.
So it has to tagle between the main
thread and the uh executor thread. So it
is like you cannot really control that
actually like it execute in the proper
order.
So likewise like we have this executor
invoked for the uh converter. There is
some calculation happened and like
finally uh we have the result printed
here and then like finally we see like
the overall uh state becomes idle and
the workflow finished. So likewise like
you know you can use these events uh to
capture all the information that you are
interested in. So these are all the
built-in events right? We can also have
some custom events. So in this case if
you just come over here I'm going to
create something called uh resume
processed event. So I'm going to pass
some information the workflow is going
to process the resume and like when it
process the resume it is going to emit
this. So it is going to just emit uh the
processed resume processed event. This
event will have the these information
candidate name and the score. So if I
just come over here so these are all the
candidates that I'm having right. So
when you start the workflow, if I just
you know start the workflow run stream,
it is exactly the same thing here,
right? Only thing is that this time
around I will be looking for this
particular event uh you know resume
processed event because like when the
workflow executes if I just come over
here uh to the you know uh to the
executor here I'm saying that hey like
you throw uh this particular event. So
instead of just a context dot send a
message or output yield output I also
can send a event. So I'm just saying
like trigger a event. These are all the
values that you know you will be
exposing to because like if I just come
over here there is a constructor that
takes all of these information. If you
just see like the candidate name and the
score it takes. So that's why like I am
passing all of these information to this
particular class and like that will be
created as a event that I can capture
here and I can print these values here.
So now if I run it here,
if you see here, if you just come over
here, if you see like workflow started,
workflow in progress and like these are
all the events reported like as the
workflow executed, it triggered all of
these custom events and that can also be
captured. Now next thing is that uh we
will be looking into the possible event.
So basically like using these events you
can control the execution. So like let's
say like I have a refund processor. So
the user will be asking for a refund. If
it is under $100 that will be auto
approved. But if it is more than $100
then the human needs to decide whether
they wanted to approve it or not. So if
you see here I have a data class. So
data data class it's called uh refund
request. It has the order ID and the
amount. And if you see here like I have
a refund processor. It has the handler
class and the response handler class. So
what is the difference between handler
class? Handler class we already know
like when you when you make a call uh by
passing all these uh you know
information the handler will
automatically get called. But what is
this response handler? So when you use
this request info, if you see here uh
hey like first when it is less than $100
we will send back to the call uh you
know caller saying that hey this request
it's approved auto approved but if it is
greater than $100 then we don't want to
send a message rather like we wanted to
request for information when you say
request for information it will the
workflow will know that hey like I need
a information from external system it
can be a human being or it can be
external system that will pass me that
information with that information I will
execute the rest of the uh task as a
part of this particular workflow. So
here like I'm saying like a request info
the request data I I need to pass two
information request data and response
type right I will be passing this data
data it's like what it's passed to this
particular executor I will be sending
the same information so basically it's
nothing but the order id and the uh
amount that will be passed and the
response type I wanted to get the
response from the external system or a
human uh saying that approved or
rejected or whatever is that right So I
will be expecting the response of type
string. That's what I'm saying here. So
when you have this when somebody
responded back to this particular
request then this response handler will
get called. So now if you see here uh
now here like we know feedback we have
if the feedback is yes then the status
will be approved otherwise it will be
rejected right. So now you know like
when the response handler will get
called whenever somebody is uh you know
responding back to your request then
this response handler will get called.
So now if I just come over here this
workflow uh I am you know starting a
workflow with a message orderer id uh is
whatever is that amount is $500 I am
sending. So now what will happen is that
the workflow will get started. The
executor will get invoked and like the
executor when it sees $500 it will come
over here. When he sees $500 it will
request for information. So this
particular event will get called. So if
the event of a type request info event
then what I want to do is that I want to
print this message in the console saying
that hey like human approval needed for
this particular amount do you approve
you say yes or no then the response will
be captured here the response will be
sent back uh to the uh workflow again.
So now I'm just capturing this. If I
just come over here, the way you send
the response back to the workflow
workflow dot send a response streaming
like whatever the response that you
have. So basically like it will have two
things. One is the request ID and the
response. So that will be part of this
pending response. I will be passing it
to the workflow. Now workflow will have
the request ID like what is the like for
each request will have its own ID and
for that particular request what is the
response or received both will be uh
combined and sent back to the workflow
using this particular method send a
response streaming when when we call
this method send a response streaming
with the request ID and the response
this particular method will get called a
response handler will get called. Now
you will have two information one the uh
original request and like the feedback.
So based on which we can um the rest of
the workflow will get executed. Now let
me go ahead and clear this console. Now
let me go ahead and run this program.
So if you see here it says that hey like
a human approval needed for $500. Do you
approve or no? I see like I approve. Now
it says that like the final outcome for
this one human approved. Now if I say
again, now if I say no, it will say that
it is rejected by the human. This
workflow it's not a static workflow.
Basically it's a dynamic workflow,
right? Though like we pass the uh you
know a decision uh in the console which
we don't do it in the uh real world but
for a purpose of demonstrating I'm just
showcasing that the workflow can get the
response from a external system. In this
case like it is the same console. I'm
just passing this information but it
shows the ability for the workflow to
get the response from the external
system. Let's move forward and discuss
about the checkpoint. So checkpoint it's
a way of storing the workflow state. Uh
say like you have a longunning workflow.
You wanted to pause the workflow and
restart the workflow. at the time you
have to save the state and reload the
state before you can you know run the
workflow again or like the system
crashes you want to continue the
workflow from where it left off then you
have to save the state of these workflow
so what are all the instances where the
states get saved or checkpoint get
created right so you think of like a
workflow with the different life events
so say like the workflow initiated
workflow passed workflow resumed
workflow completed. So all these kind of
a events will trigger a checkpoint
creation and what gets saved in the
checkpoint. So typically the uh executor
state and then like the message like you
say you you want to send a message from
one executor to another exeutor that
message gets stored and then like you
will you can have a shared state and you
will also have a pending request. Say
like you want to pass the workflow for a
user input then you will be having the
pending request. So all this information
will get stored in the checkpoint. Now
let's go back to the visual studio code
and see how do we implement the
checkpoint. So if you see here like I'm
using the file checkpoint storage
likewise you also have a in-memory
checkpoint storage and if at all you
wanted to have a you know custom uh
checkpoint storage you can very well
create one but in this case I will be
using the file uh checkpoint storage to
store the checkpoint basically it's a
JSON file that will get stored and this
is the folder where I wanted to store my
JSON file basically the state file right
so if you see here the workflow by
itself itself. It's a pretty simple uh
flow. You run the workflow, it is going
to request for a user feedback by using
this particular data class here. So if I
just come over here, so what I am doing
here is that I'm creating a file
checkpoint storage using the path that
we mentioned that I'm creating a
workflow. If you see here, this is the
only node that it will have and like I'm
creating the workflow with the
checkpoint and I use the file checkpoint
storage class here. So with that like I
created a workflow and when I run the
workflow uh it will just go here right
and it will ask for a user input. Now at
this moment the workflow will get paused
right. So now uh up to this point it
will create two JSON file. when we
initialize the workflow, it will create
the very first JSON file and then like
when it reach the you know the user
input state then it is going to create
the second uh state file. Now uh if you
see here I am you know getting all the
checkpoints I'm getting the uh last
checkpoint
uh ID here and like I will store this
information with me. Now I am deleting
this particular workflow. Basically like
I'm just deleting the instance of this
workflow. Let's assume that at this
point in time the system crashed. The
workflow instance got destroyed. Now I
don't have anything. All I have is this
checkpoint ID. Right? Now what I will do
is that I will create a workflow again.
Exactly the same configuration. Right?
Because like we wanted to have the same
workflow. Now what I want to do is that
I want to rehydrate the workflow. Now
what I want to do is that I want to
bring the new workflow instance to the
old state. So the way I do it's like I
will run the workflow by using the run
stream but I will be passing the
checkpoint ID. So technically what it
will do is that it will go back and you
know look at the checkpoint files that
we have. It will rerun the workflow and
bring the new workflow instance to the
old state. Now it will reach the request
info event just because like we are
asking for the user uh input here right
request info. Now it will reach that
point. Now I will capture the request ID
here. Now what I will do is that if
there is a request ID then I want to
call the send a response or streaming by
passing the request ID and then like the
response response I hardcoded here
saying approved. So what it will do is
that it will take that request ID and
then like it will pass the response as
approved. Now it will go back here
right. So it will go back to the human
feedback. The human feedback will say
decision it's approved for the amount
like whatever it's that right now with
that like we will be completing the
workflow. Now let me go ahead and uh run
this uh flow here. If you see here uh we
started the workflow and like the
workflow passed for a user request and
like we created a checkpoint. Now the
system crashed. Now we resume the
workflow by using the checkpoint ID that
we created.
Now we have the uh you know request ID
here and like it is approved. So now if
I just go here to the temp folder. So if
you see here, so these are all the uh
checkpoints are created for me. So if I
just open here, so this is iteration
two. Now let me find the iteration one.
Yeah, this is the iteration first. So
this is the very first time the JSON
file got created. Right? So it is
pending for the uh user input. Right?
Now this is the very first time the
state file got created. Now this is
iteration two. Right? So when we uh
rehydrate using the checkpoint ID uh you
know this will reach this particular
state at that time there is going to be
another JSON file get created. Now uh
with that like we say approved so that
is also captured here that is part of a
message that you will see here. Then
finally the workflow got completed here
because like there is nothing pending
there is no message there is no pending
there is no uh shared state as well. Now
the workflow got completed. So now I
don't want to have the hard-coded
approval. So I want to combine both the
checkpoint and the uh external approval
together in a workflow. Right? So now
let's go ahead and uh have a look at
that. So if you see here this is exactly
the same uh workflow but if you see here
instead of you know hard coding that uh
approval what I want to do is that I
want to ask for the input and I will
pass that input. So it's very simple. So
now let me go ahead and uh run this
program. So if you see here it is asking
for the user input. Now let's say I
approve this. So it says that the final
decision it's approved for this
particular amount. Now let me go and run
it again. This time I will say deny. So
it says that the final decision it's
deny. So this is how you can combine
both the checkpoint and the uh external
approval system together. Now what I
want to do is that I don't want to do
everything in the console rather like I
wanted to replicate the real world use
case right now let me go and use this
particular program. Now let me go ahead
and run this program.
So if you see here let me maximize this.
So if you see here it is saying that uh
you know refund approval required. So
here it says that amount it's this is
the order number reason is this whatever
is that. So here you can see approve or
deny or partial approve or whatever is
that. Now if you see that human approved
for a refund whatever is that order
number whatever is that and amount
whatever is that. Now it also displays
all the uh checkpoint information here.
Now if you see here like I'm doing
everything through the console again.
Now think of this way like there will be
two set of a people. the first set of a
person who will be rising for a refund
request and there is going to be a
second set of a people who will be
approving this request. Now let's see
how do we do that. Now let me go ahead
and run this program. So if you see here
like we are running our program uh
locally using the fast API. Now let me
go ahead and uh open this. Let's assume
that the you know user it's rising for a
refund request for order ID 101. The
reason it's a defective right. So now
let's assume that you are a you know
another uh user who will be rising for a
refund request for some something for
damaged right so now we have two
different uh refund request now approver
comes in he can approve or he can delay
right so everything it's done uh through
fast API so what it does is that behind
the scenes it uses the workflow now we
can go back to the visual studio and see
like what has happened behind the
scenes. So if you just come over here
you will see all these API calls here
and if you see here like it is making a
call to the task and you know performing
the uh decision like when you click on
the approve or you know deny uh this
particular endp point will get called.
Now again let me go here. Now if I try
to add uh one more item here three uh
say like 500. If I just come over here,
so it is just going to create a refund
here. So behind the scenes, what it will
do is that it will create a uh entry in
the task. JSON like I'm not using the
database, but like you can very well use
the database to store all the refund
request. Consider this as a refund
request. So somebody writes a request
for order number three for the reason is
this. How somebody needs to approve
that. Now as a approver you will come
over here you approve or deny whatever
is that you click on that then again
like when you click on that this
particular task will get called uh and
the decision will be made. So if you
just come over here all this information
will be stored in the uh checkpoint
file. So that's how like we are able to
pass and you know retrieve the uh you
know workflow and execute the workflow.
If I just go back to the code again,
it is the pretty simple code, right? If
you see like this is where like we are
storing the checkpoint and if I just
come over here, it is exactly the same
kind of a workflow that we have here,
right? So if I just come over here, we
just build the workflow as the way we
did it, right? And like when we want to
run the workflow, we will just run
stream. We will just run stream. use the
run stream and like whenever we wanted
to make a decision right so what we need
to do we need to do the checkpoint we
use the checkpoint and we will pass the
uh approval right so we will pass the
approval so this is where like we will
pass the decision here so that's how you
can build the real world workflows and
integrate with your uh APIs using this
kind of a pattern you can very well
build the really powerful workflows
that can be integrated with your
application. Now finally we will see how
do we use the observability. In one of
the previous video I already discussed
about the observability. So if you see
here exactly the same thing it's what we
are going to apply here. We will have a
span. The span will contain all the
relevant information. So we will make
use of this span to extract all the
information. So now let's go back and
see how do we do this. So now let me go
ahead and clear this console. So let me
run it. If you see here it is going to
create a text file for me. So if I just
come over here. So this is what we have
here. Like if I go to the program again
this is a pretty simple program uh
simple sequential workflow from writer
to SEO to the editor. And this is what
you know we are interested in right. So
if you just come over here it says that
hey like initially we started the build
process that took about uh you know this
much time then the orchestrated
basically the workflow send a message to
the initial uh executor and the this is
the message passed and the like this
writer respond back to the orchestrator.
So the orchestrator send a message to
the SEO all this information. Now SEO
was sent back to orchestrator.
Orchestrator sent back to editor. Editor
completed and it sent back to the
orchestrator. Orchestrator received
finally we printed. So if you see this
you can tell the complete story right?
So you can always use the obserability
for this particular purpose. So if you
think of this way on the one hand you
have the events on the other hand you
have the observability which one to use.
So basically the events are not
necessarily meant for observability
though that can be used to export some
of these information.
It serves a different purpose. You can
use the events for observability. You
can use the events to control your
workflow. You can use the events to you
know calculate the percentage of know
task completed. All of these can be done
with events. On the other hand,
observability it's the industry standard
that captures the telemetry across the
execution. So you can use both of these
for your observability.
So that's all I have for this video. Uh,
thank you for watching.